Guide to the Walter B. Gibson Papers, 1943-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Walter B. Gibson papers 1943-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Gibson, Walter B.
0.6 Linear Feet 450 Items
Walter B. Gibson (1897-1985) was a professional magician and author, who often wrote under the name Maxwell Grant, and is credited with defining and popularizing the pulp hero, The Shadow.
The collection includes: Two Shadow story outlines, one from 1943 and another from 1980, which was Gibson's last Shadow story; 97 radio scripts from Strange, a seemingly lost 15-minute program that Gibson hosted in 1955; an unproduced television proposal, Mike Regan, Confidential Investigator, circa the mid 1950s; and two bookplates featuring a black and white image of The Shadow.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Walter B. Gibson Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2010.
Biographical and Historical Note
Walter B. Gibson (1897-1985) was a professional magician and author, who often wrote under the name Maxwell Grant, and is credited with defining and popularizing the pulp hero, The Shadow. The character started as the narrator for the radio show, Detective Story Hour, but became so popular that he inspired his own magazine. Gibson was hired to write the pulp which he did with staggering frequency, producing 282 of the 325 Shadow pulp novels, starting with the character's debut in 1931 and ending in the late 1940s. Years later Gibson published three final Shadow novels, including what would be his last story, The Blackmail Bay, in 1980. Gibson wrote for a wide variety of publications and other mediums including television and film, but often as a ghost writer. Today he is primarily know for The Shadow, which spawned numerous imitators, Batman being the most notable.
Collection Overview
The collection includes: Two Shadow story outlines, one from 1943 and another from 1980, which was Gibson's last Shadow story; 97 radio scripts from Strange, a seemingly lost 15-minute program that Gibson hosted in 1955; an unproduced television proposal, Mike Regan, Confidential Investigator, circa the mid 1950s; and two bookplates featuring a black and white image of The Shadow.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Gibson, Walter B. (Walter Brown), 1897-1985
Grant, Maxwell, 1897-1985
Mass media -- History -- 20th century
Outlines (documents)
Radio broadcasting -- History -- United States
Radio scripts
Shadow (Fictitious character)
Television -- Proposals
Contents of Collection
- Scripts and Story Outlines, 1943-1980, (1 box)
  - Outline for The Shadow Magazine: The Muggers Murders, November 1943 (Box 1)
  - Outline for The Shadow Magazine: Blackmail Bay, 1980
  - Television proposal: Mike Regan, Confidential Investigator, undated
  - Strange radio show scripts, 1955
    - Episodes 1-15, 1955 May 31-1955 June 21
    - Episodes 16-30, 1955 June 22-1955 July 12
    - Episodes 31-45, 1955 July 18-1955 August 2
    - Episodes 46-60, 1955 August 3-1955 August 23
    - Episodes 61-75, 1955 August 24-1955 September 13
    - Episodes 76-88, 1955 September 14-1955 October 6
    - Episodes 89-97, 1955 October 7-1955 October 25